A Guide to the Susana Torre Architectural Papers, 1967-2003
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Susana Torre Architectural Papers, 1967-2003
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1990-016
24.4 cu. ft. (21 boxes, 21 oversize folders, 3 framed drawings, and 1 model)
After earning her degree in architecture in Buenos Aires, Argentinean Susana Torre arrived in New York in 1968 to study and practice architecture. Women's place in architecture and renovation of buildings are topics of particular interest to her. The Susana Torre papers consist of professional correspondence, project files, architectural drawings and sketches of some of her works, research notes, published articles about and by Torre, and teaching notes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Susana Torre Architectural Papers were donated to the International Archive of Women in Architecture in 1990 by their creator. Additional material was donated in 1998, 2000, and 2003.
Alternate Form Available
Selected images of work by Torre are available in the VT Imagebase.
Biographical/Historical Information
Susana Torre was born in 1944 in Argentina and graduated from the University of Buenos Aires with a degree in architecture and additional course work in urban planning in 1967. In 1968 she moved to the United States to pursue post-graduate studies in urban planning at Columbia University. Her career following the completion of her studies was based in New York City. Susana Torre was a principal of the Architectural Studio in New York from 1978 to 1984. She also worked as a partner at Wank Adams Slavin Associates and Torre Beeler Associates before starting an independent practice, Susana Torre and Associates of New York, in 1989. She has been associated with the Museum of Modern Art's Department of Architecture and Design and served as the coordinator of a research study on six new towns for the Institute for Architecture and Urban Studies. Torre also has held academic appointments at Columbia University, SUNY at Old Westbury, Barnard College Architecture Program, and New Jersey Institute of Technology as well as serving as a visiting critic and adjunct professor at other schools in the New York area.
Throughout her career, Torre has been concerned with the status of women in architecture, studying the history of the subject and advocating fuller participation of women in the field. Her work is strongly engaged in a dialogue of Modernist and Post-modernist forms. Susana Torre has received several awards, including recognition from the Edgar Kaufman Foundation and the National Endowment for the Arts. Torre has served on national juries for the American Institute of Architects (AIA) as well as other educational institutions. She is well known for her renovation and remodeling projects such as the master plan for the restoration of Ellis Island in New York Harbor (1981); renovation of Clark House, a turn-of-the-century carriage house in South Hampton, New York (1982) which received an Award of Excellence of Design from Architectural Record; the renovation of Schermerhorn Hall at Columbia University (1985); and Fire Station Five in Columbus, Indiana (1987).
Torre has published many articles in journals, newspapers, and magazines and has exhibited works at the Museum of Modern Art, The Institute for Architecture and Urban Studies, The Otis Art Institute, MIT's Hayden Gallery, and the Cooper Hewitt Museum. Ms. Torre was the editor, curator and designer of the exhibit "Women in Architecture: A Historic and Contemporary Perspective," that toured United States in 1977 and the complementary book of essays (1977) that accompanied it.
Scope and Content
The Susana Torre Architectural Papers consist of twenty-four cubic feet of material including professional correspondence, project files, research notes, published articles, office files about and by Torre, and teaching notes amassed by Torre, as well as twenty folders of architectural drawings and sketches, and photographs of projects taken before, during and after construction, mostly during the period from 1968 to 1991. The collection also includes three framed drawings and a model of the Garvey residence at Amagansett, Long Island. The information focuses on Torre's professional career, with the bulk of the material covering architectural projects and publishing and teaching efforts.
The project files include contracts, bids and proposals, project notes, feasibility studies, correspondence with clients and builders, specifications, product information, and clippings of articles about the projects. There are also seventeen sets of project drawings. The most important and best-documented projects of this collection are the renovation of a law office for Harry Torcyzner, New York; the Clark's residence at South Hampton, New York; the Chamber's Street Restaurant, New York; the Embassy of the Ivory Coast; the Robert Panero Associates office renovation project; a feasibility study for "Suitables" (a chain of women's clothing stores); the renovation of Schemerhorn Hall at Columbia University, New York; the Fire Station Five at Columbus, Indiana; the Montauk Public Library, New York; a fire station in Jersey City, New Jersey; a feasibility study for the Ruppert Green Project (a multi-family residential complex in New Jersey); the Garvey residence; the Feinberg residence in Chillmark, Massachusetts; Columbia University's Law Library renovation; and the Jewett Arts Center at Wellesley College, MA.
Professional papers include information about associations and organizations in which Torre participated; organizational correspondence regarding meetings, objectives and proceedings, invitations, brochures and articles about speakers and organization events; publications by and about Torre and architecture; and Torre's notes about women in architecture that she used to prepare the 1977 exhibition and its companion book, Women in American Architecture. Organizations to which Torre belonged include the Architectural League of New York, the Heresies (a feminist publication on art and politics), Networks: Women in Architecture, the Journal of Architectural Education (JAE), the International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA), the Association of Collegiate Schools of Architecture (ASCA): Task Force on the Status of Women in Architecture Schools, and Architects Designers Planners for Social Responsibility (ADPSR). The publications span the dates 1967-1992 and include early Spanish-language and later English material written by Torre, as well as magazine and newspaper clippings, invitations to conferences and technical paper presentations, outlines of articles and comments on other author's publications, correspondence with publishers and organizations, and Torre's hand-written notes from meetings and conferences.
There are also accumulated research notes about women architects in America that Torre compiled to write the introduction and several segments of the book Women in American Architecture: a Historic and Contemporary Perspective that received support from the Architectural League of New York and was published by Whitney Library of Design. The exhibition opened at the Brooklyn Museum in 1977 and then toured around the United States. The research files include information about specific architects, general notes and photographs, and articles and papers published by American women architects.
Faculty papers include lecture notes, student projects, newspaper clippings and theses from lecture and teaching positions that Torre held at schools such as State University of New York (SUNY) at Old Westbury, the Pratt Institute, Syracuse University, Miami University in Ohio, Columbia University and its Graduate School of Architecture Planning and preservation program, University of Pennsylvania, Escula Technica Superior De Architectura in Spain, Barnard Architecture College, University of Sydney, New Jersey Institute of Technology, and New Jersey School of Architecture.
Office Files include correspondence documents, notes, brochures and invitations for lectures, conference and symposia attended and participated in by Torre spanning from 1967 to 1994. The collection also includes information about the various exhibitions, juries, and advisory boards in which Torre participated, helped organize, and presided over during her professional career. The Awards and Fellowships files include documentation and information regarding the various awards, honors, and fellowships that Torre received from 1979 to 1990.
Arrangement
The Susana Torre Collection is arranged in four series reflecting architectural projects, work with professional organizations, teaching, and office work.
Series I, Project Files, consists of project files and some sets of architectural drawings. The project information is arranged chronologically. Some projects have been assigned circa dates, reflecting the fact that although they do not have specific dates, they were filed in the order that Torre worked on them.
Series II, Professional Papers, contains three subseries of material: (A) Professional and Cultural Organizations, (B) Publications, and (C) Research Files. Subseries A and C are arranged chronologically, and subseries B is grouped by topic and arranged alphabetically.
Series III, Faculty Papers, contains material Torre used and collected while teaching at universities. The material is arranged by the name of the school with which it is associated, and chronologically within each school grouping.
Series IV, Office Files, contains five subseries: (A) Lectures, (B) Conferences and Symposia, (C) Juries and Advisory Boards, (D) Exhibitions, and (E) Awards and Fellowships. All are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Series I: Project Records 1971-1989
  - Circulo Condominum Apartments, n.d. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Office for Natalio Schwartz, Washington Heights, New York, NY, n.d. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - "Nature Series" Design for Bedsheets, 1971 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - "The House of Meanings" designed for Dr. Natalio Schwartz, Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Book design for Tuten's "The Adventures of Mao on the Long March," 1971-1972 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Simone Sman "House of Meanings in Rincon, Puerto Rico," 1972 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - The Women's Interart Center Gallery and Performance Space, New York, NY, 1972 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Building Condition Assessment, Embassy of the Ivory Coast, 1972 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Pre-Schematics for "Courage: My Love - A Restaurant Gallery," New York, NY, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Building Condition Assessment, Danjedon Corporation, 1973 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Architectural Studio, Susana Torre, "A Space Without a Function" - Article 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Architectural Studio: Stationary Design, NY, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Roosevelt Island Housing Competition, 1975 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Law Office Renovation, Harry Torcyzner, NY, 1976
    - Project records (Box-folder 1:14)
    - Architectural Drawings (Oversize 1)
  - Kuchin House Alterations, 1977-78
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 1:15)
    - Existing Conditions and Preliminary Stair Studies (Box-folder 1:16)
    - Products and systems (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Schematics (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Clark Residence, 1977-1980
    - Administration (Box-folder 1:19)
    - Contract (Box-folder 1:20)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 1:21)
    - Existing Conditions and Surveys (Box-folder 1:22)
    - Landscaping (Box-folder 1:23)
    - Products (Box-folder 1:24)
    - Architectural Drawings (Oversize 2)
  - Proposal for four Mental Health Clinics in the Dominican Republic (with Roger Ferri), 1977 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Bach House, 1977-1978
    - Administration (Box-folder 1:26)
    - Materials and Assemblies (Box-folder 1:27)
    - Schematics (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Consulate, Ivory Coast, 1977 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Puglia Competition, 1977 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Wedding House, n.d. (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Walter Barley Griffin Memorial Competition, n.d. (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Deck for Lucy Uppdro, Georgetown, ME, n.d. (Box-folder 1:33)
  - "The Children's Storefront," Harlem, NY, n.d. (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Condo Renovations, Kyanstan Meshine, n.d. (Box-folder 1:35)
  - Residence, Susanne Stephen, n.d. (Box-folder 1:36)
  - 4th Federal Design Assembly, 1978
    - Site (Box-folder 1:37)
    - Administraion (Box-folder 1:38)
    - Federal Design Improvement Plan (Box-folder 9a:1)
  - Standards for Office Construction, Chris McNeur, 1978 (Box-folder 1:39)
  - Preliminary Property Assessment, Mr. Dwoughi, Ivory Coast, n.d. (Box-folder 1:40)
  - Dragon Inn Restaurant, NJ, 1978
    - Trial documents (Box-folder 1:41)
    - Agreement documents (Box-folder 1:42)
    - Notes, drawings and magazine clippings (Box-folder 1:43)
    - Estimates and bills (Box-folder 1:44)
  - Embassy of the Ivory Coast, 1978-1980
    - Construction Documents and Notes (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Cost Estimates (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Furniture (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Photographs of Existing Conditions (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Products and Installations (Box-folder 2:6-7)
    - Shop Drawings (Box-folder 2:8)
    - Architectural Drawings (Oversize 3)
  - Chambers Street Restaurant, 1978-1979
    - Administration and Notes (Box-folder 2:9)
    - Contract and Administration (Box-folder 2:10)
    - Photographs of Existing Conditions (Box-folder 2:11)
    - Products and Installations (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Schematics (Folder 2:13)
    - Sketches and Notes (Box-folder 2:14)
    - Architectural Drawings (Oversize 4-5)
  - Residence for Eugenia Rendon de Olazabal, NY, 1979-1980
    - Correspondence and notes (Box-folder 2:15)
    - Contractor and builder correspondence (Box-folder 2:16)
    - Client correspondence (Box-folder 2:17)
    - Project drawings and sketches (Box-folder 2:18)
    - Magazine clippings (Box-folder 2:19)
  - Alterations, Cherio Corporation, NY, 1979 (Box-folder 2:20-21)
  - Curbelo Kitchen, ca. 1979 (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Brenda Miller Book Design, ca. 1979 (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Center for Inter-American Relations, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2:24)
  - The Women's Studio Workshop, 1979 (Box-folder 2:25)
  - Muniak House, NY, 1979 (Box-folder 2:26)
  - Feasibility Study, Chelsea, NY, 1979 (Box-folder 2:27)
  - Sculpture Project, Sol Lewitt, 1980 (Box-folder 2:28)
  - "Wire Ponies," ca. 1980 (Box-folder 2:29)
  - PSI Room, Institute of Art and Urban Resources, ca. 1980 (Box-folder 2:30)
  - Illinois Regional Library for The Blind and Physically Handicapped, ca. 1980 (Box-folder 2:31)
  - New Jersey Bylaws and Regulations, ca. 1980 (Box-folder 2:32)
  - Robert Panero Associates, 1980-1981
    - Articles (Box-folder 2:33)
    - Bills and samples (Box-folder 2:34)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 2:35)
    - Estimates (Box-folder 2:36)
    - Estimates of products (Box-folder 2:37)
    - Architectural Drawings (Oversize 6)
  - Ruppert Green, ca. 1980
    - Scheme drawings (Box-folder 3:1)
    - Zoning analysis (Box-folder 3:2)
    - Architectural Drawings (Oversize 7)
  - Feasibility study, Union Square Manhattan, ca. 1980 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - "Suitables" Store, 1980
    - Feasibility study (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Architectural Drawings (Oversize 8)
  - Vassar College, NY, 1980 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Apartment for Laura Eastman, ca. 1980 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Blackwood Films Consulting, 1980 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Pelham Parkway Mall, 1981
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 3:8)
    - Guidelines and specifications (Box-folder 3:9)
    - Consultant contract (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Loft Renovation, Larrisa, ca. 1981 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Bus Garage, West Side Highway Project (with Bend Ryder Associates), 1981 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Excavation Estimates for Sol-Lewitt Wall, Chicago, IL, 1981 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Retirement Home for Geoffrey Fox's Parents, Arizona, 1981 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Eastern Office Park Consulting, Puerto Rico, 1981 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Studies for Torre's New Office, n.d. (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Astoria Studio Proposal, 1981 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Caracas Night Club Project, Venezuela, 1981 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Retirement Home Advice for Stanley Harn, 1982 (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Ellis Island Proposal, Leading Edge Products, Canton, MA, 1982 (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Frenkel Residence Alterations, New Preston, CT, 1982
    - Administration (Box-folder 3:21)
    - Client's Magazine Clippings (Box-folder 3:22)
    - Photographs and Slides (Box-folder 3:23)
  - Schermerhorn Hall, Colombia University, New York, NY, 1982-1986
    - Auditorium seating (Box-folder 3:24)
    - Budgets and estimates (Box-folder 3:25)
    - Budgets and estimates (Box-folder 3:26)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 3:27-29)
    - Design development (Box-folder 3:30-32)
    - Design development, Book 2 (Box-folder 4:1)
    - Design development submission notes (Box-folder 4:2)
    - Drawings list (Box-folder 4:3)
    - Drawings and photographs (Box-folder 4:4)
    - Existing Furniture (Box-folder 4:5)
    - Existing Furniture Photographs (Box-folder 4:6)
    - Finish Schedule (Box-folder 4:7)
    - Fire protection plan (Box-folder 4:8)
    - Furniture estimations (Box-folder 4:9)
    - Furniture specifications (Box-folder 4:10)
    - Humidification and HVAC (Box-folder 4:11)
    - Insurance (Box-folder 4:12)
    - Lighting Fixtures (Box-folder 4:13)
    - Measurements and computations (Box-folder 4:14)
    - Minutes (Box-folder 4:15-16)
    - Miscellaneous Documents (Box-folder 4:17)
    - Model notes (Box-folder 4:18)
    - Organizing systems lists (Box-folder 4:19)
    - Phasing (Box-folder 4:20)
    - Photo Documentation (Box-folder 4:21)
    - Products (Box-folder 4:22)
    - Program notes (Box-folder 4:23)
    - Projection cabinets (Box-folder 4:24)
    - Psychology Department (Box-folder 4:25)
    - Punch List (Box-folder 4:26)
    - Research (Box-folder 4:27)
    - Saved jottings (Box-folder 4:28)
    - Schematic Design (Box-folder 4:29)
    - Security Systems (Box-folder 4:30)
    - Signage Systems (Box-folder 4:31)
    - Sketches (Box-folder 4:32)
    - Specifications and correspondence (Box-folder 4:33)
    - Structural Systems (Box-folder 4:34)
    - Windows (Box-folder 4:35)
    - Architectural Drawings (Oversize 9-10)
  - Monroeville Civic Center, Pittsburgh, PA, 1982
    - Administration (Box-folder 5:1)
    - Research Documents (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Report (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Preliminary Sketches for House for Susana Torre, Carbonerras, Spain, n.d. (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Cornubia Hall Alterations, 1982 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Interior Layout for Artist's Co-op, Forsyth Street, New York, NY, n.d. (Box-folder 5:6)
  - River Front Plaza Design Competition, Ft. Lauderdale, FL, n.d. (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Office Layout for Heresies, A Feminist Publication, n.d. (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Consulting for Meadowlands Park, NJ, 1983 (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Proposal for Sir George University Shop, n.d. (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Proposal for House Addition, Weiselblat, NY, 1983 (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Spectacle Island Design Competition, Boston Harbor, 1983 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Office Renovation for APERTURE Magazine, New York, NY, 1983 (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Gazebo Retreat, Harry Torczyner, Peekshill, NY, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - New York Law School, 1983 (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Recording Studio Survey, New York, NY, 1983 (Box-folder 5:16)
  - Chemical Bank Gallery, NY, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 5:17)
  - The Smithsonian Design Charrette, Washington DC, 1983-84 (Box-folder 5:18)
  - Harlem Housing Charrette, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 5:19)
  - Lighting for Stett Heimer Exhibit, Avery Library, New York, NY, 1983 (Box-folder 5:20)
  - Fire Station Five, Columbus, IN, 1983-1988
    - Brochures (Box-folder 5:21)
    - Brochures and Schematics (Box-folder 5:22)
    - Contract (Box-folder 5:23)
    - Construction (Box-folder 5:24)
    - Construction and Communication (Box-folder 5:25)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 5:26)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 5:27)
    - Landscaping (Box-folder 5:28)
    - Lighting (Box-folder 5:29)
    - Materials and Systems (Box-folder 5:30)
    - Mechanical (Box-folder 5:31)
    - Minutes (Box-folder 5:32)
    - Structural Documents (Box-folder 5:33)
    - Architectural Drawings (Oversize 11)
  - Fordham University Dormitory, 1984 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Sam P. Harn Museum of Fine Arts, Gainesville, FL, 1984 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Ronald Feldman Gallery Installation "On Post Modern Space," 1984 (Box-folder 6:3-4)
  - Franklin Funds Office Renovation, 1984-1985
    - Administration (Box-folder 6:5-6)
    - Products and specifications (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Metairie Park Country Day School, LA, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Battery Park City, New York, NY, 1984 (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Jacobs' Pillow Design Festival Competition, 1984 (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Herman Miller, 1984 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - LaGuardia Community College, 1984 (Box-folder 7:12)
  - Residence for Garvey, Amagansett, NY, 1984-1987
    - Garvey Residence, Article "Family Circles" by Scott Guttermann in Architectural Record Houses, 1988 (Box-folder 6:13)
    - Bathrooms (Box-folder 6:14)
    - Bidding (Box-folder 6:15)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 6:16)
    - Cost Estimate (Box-folder 6:17)
    - Drawings of topographic map of site (Box-folder 6:18)
    - Frigidaire (Box-folder 6:19)
    - Furniture and Equipment (Box-folder 6:20)
    - Hardware (Box-folder 6:21)
    - Invoices (Box-folder 6:22)
    - Kitchen (Box-folder 6:23)
    - Lighting and Heating (Box-folder 6:24)
    - Miscellaneous interior hardware (Box-folder 6:25)
    - Notes of conversations with clients (Box-folder 6:26)
    - Photographs (Box-folder 6:27)
    - Photographs of models and plans (Box-folder 6:28)
    - Program (Box-folder 6:29)
    - Schedule (Box-folder 6:30)
    - Sketches (Box-folder 6:31)
    - Slides (Box-folder 6:32)
    - Window details (Box-folder 6:33)
    - Three framed colored architectural drawings - Site Plan, Floor Plan, Elevations (Frame 3 Framed Watercolors)
    - Model of Residence for Garvey (Othertype 1 architectural model)
  - UC Berkley-Urban Design Charrette, n.d. (Box-folder 6:34)
  - Columbia Law School, 1984 (Box-folder 6:35)
  - Residence for Feinberg, Chillmark, MA, 1985-1986
    - Bidding documents (Box-folder 6:36)
    - Bills and transmittals (Box-folder 6:37)
    - Bylaws and contracts (Box-folder 6:38)
    - Construction sketches (Box-folder 6:39)
    - Fireplace details (Box-folder 6:40)
    - Furniture (Box-folder 6:41)
    - Notes and correspondence (Box-folder 6:42)
    - Notes (Box-folder 6:43)
    - Products (Box-folder 6:44)
    - Program (Box-folder 6:45)
    - Project schedule (Box-folder 6:46)
    - Reimbursement (Box-folder 6:47)
    - Scheme designs (Box-folder 6:48)
    - Site zoning (Box-folder 6:49)
    - Specifications (Box-folder 6:50)
  - Montauk Public Library, Montauk, NY, 1985-1989
    - Addenda (Box-folder 7:1)
    - Application for Payment (Box-folder 7:2)
    - Area/Park/Book count (Box-folder 7:3)
    - Bidders (Box-folder 7:4)
    - Bid Documentation (Box-folder 7:5)
    - Bid Documentation (Box-folder 7:6)
    - Bid Information (Box-folder 7:7)
    - Book Stacks (Box-folder 7:8)
    - Bonds, Certificiates (Box-folder 7:9)
    - Borings (Box-folder 7:10)
    - Brochure (Box-folder 7:11)
    - Building Permit (Box-folder 7:12)
    - Catalog Cuts (Box-folder 7:13)
    - Clerks of Works (Box-folder 7:14)
    - Code Analysis (Box-folder 7:15)
    - Consultants (Box-folder 7:16)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 7:17-18)
    - Correspondence, Post bid (Box-folder 7:19)
    - Department of Education, Manual of Planning Standards for School Buildings (Box-folder 7:20)